Guide to the Phillip Bonosky Papers TAM.628
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Phillip Bonosky Papers
1935-2006
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Bonosky, Nora
Bonosky, Phillip
Rosenberg, Daniel
TAM.628
32 Linear Feet in 24 record cartons and 16 manuscript boxes
Phillip Bonosky (1916-2013) was a novelist and journalist who worked as a cultural editor and Moscow correspondent for the Daily World. Bonosky was a longtime member of the Communist Party USA (CPUSA), and his foreign reporting covered Moscow, Cambodia after the expulsion of the Khmer Rouge, and included interviews with figures such as Afghan leaders in the 1980s and Vietnamese revolutionary and President Hồ Chí Minh. His literary works include the 1953 coming-of-age novel Burning Valley, set during an organizing effort amongst steelworkers in Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania. The Phillip Bonosky Papers (dated 1935-2006) consists of journals, letters, and original writings by Bonosky. The majority of the collection consists of journals that contain typescript manuscripts, as well as daily accounting's of Bonosky's interpretation of domestic and international events, his involvement with the Communist Party of the United States of America (CPUSA), his journalist coverage for the Daily World, and his interactions with a wide range of leftist figures including Steve Nelson, Alexander Trachtenberg, Pettis Perry, and Claudia Jones. Significantly, Bonosky and Alice Neel spent most days together for a period of time and Bonosky's daily journaling offers a day-by-day unfolding of Neel's life as well.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Nora Bonosky in 2013. The accession number related to this gift is 2013.009. In March 2023, Daniel Rosenberg donated an accretion to the collection; the accession number associated with this gift is 2023.041.
Arrangement
Journals and arranged chronologically and manuscripts are arranged alphabetically.
Biographical Note
Phillip Bonosky (1916-2013) was a novelist and journalist who worked as a cultural editor and Moscow correspondent for the Daily World. Bonosky was a longtime member of the Communist Party USA (CPUSA), and his foreign reporting covered Moscow, Cambodia after the expulsion of the Khmer Rouge, and included interviews with figures such as Afghan leaders in the 1980s and Vietnamese revolutionary and President Hồ Chí Minh. His literary works include the 1953 coming-of-age novel Burning Valley, set during an organizing effort amongst steelworkers in Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania.
Scope and Contents
The Phillip Bonosky Papers (dated 1935-2006) consists of journals, letters, and original writings by Bonosky. The majority of the collection consists of journals that contain typescript manuscripts, as well as daily accounting's of Bonosky's interpretation of domestic and international events, his involvement with the Communist Party of the United States of America (CPUSA), his journalist coverage for the Daily World, and his interactions with a wide range of leftist figures including Steve Nelson, Alexander Trachtenberg, Pettis Perry, and Claudia Jones. Significantly, Bonosky and Alice Neel spent most days together for a period of time and Bonosky's daily journaling offers a day-by-day unfolding of Neel's life as well.
Novelists, American.; Journalists -- United States.; Communists -- United States.; Journals.; Bonosky, Nora; Rosenberg, Daniel; Neel, Alice, 1900-1984
- Journals, 1935-1938 (Box 25, Folder 1-2)
- Journals, 1941-1942 (Box 25, Folder 3-5)
- Journals, 1943 (Box 25, Folder 6-7)
- Journals, 1944 (Box 25, Folder 8, Box 26, Folder 1)
- Journals, 1945 (Box 26, Folder 2-3)
- Journals, 1946 (Box 26, Folder 4-5)
- Journals, 1947-1948 (Box 26, Folder 6)
- Journals, 1948-1955 (Box 26, Folder 7-10)
- Journals, 1949 (Box 26, Folder 11, Box 27, Folder 1-2)
- Journals, 1952-1954 (Box 27, Folder 3-6)
- Journals, 1955-1956 (Box 27, Folder 7-9)
- Journals, 1957 (Box 27, Folder 10, Box 28, Folder 1)
- Journals, 1958-1959 (Box 28, Folder 2-4)
- Journals, 1960-1962 (Box 28, Folder 5-7)
- Journals, 1963 (Box 28, Folder 8-9)
- Journals, 1964 (Box 28, Folder 10-11, Box 29, Folder 1)
- Journals, 1965-1966 (Box 29, Folder 2-5)
- Journals, 1967 (Box 29, Folder 6-8)
- Journals, 1968-1969 (Box 29, Folder 9-10, Box 30, Folder 1-2)
- Journals, 1970-1973 (Box 30, Folder 3-6)
- Journals, 1974-1975 (Box 30, Folder 7-9)
- Journals, 1976-1977 (Box 30, Folder 10, Box 31, Folder 1)
- Journals, 1978-1979 (Box 31, Folder 2-4)
- Journals, 1980-1981 (Box 31, Folder 5-7)
- Journals, 1981 (Box 31, Folder 8)
- Journals, 1982-1983 (Box 32, Folder 1)
- Journals, 1984 (Box 32, Folder 2)
- Journals, 1986-1988 (Box 32, Folder 3-4)
- Journals, 1987-1988 (Box 32, Folder 5-6)
- Journals, 1989-1990 (Box 32, Folder 7-8)
- Journals, 1991 (Box 33, Folder 1-2)
- Journals, 1992-1994 (Box 33, Folder 3-6)
- Journals, 1995-1996 (Box 33, Folder 7-9)
- Journals, 1997-1999 (Box 33, Folder 10, Box 34, Folder 1-3)
- Journals, 2000-2003 (Box 34, Folder 4-7)
- Journals, 2004 (Box 34, Folder 8-9, Box 35, Folder 1-2)
- Journals, 2006 (Box 35, Folder 3)
- Journals, 2000s (Box 35, Folder 4-6)
- Journals, undated (Box 35, Folder 7-11, Box 36, Folder 1-9, Box 37, Folder 1-5)
- Letters to Joan, 1936-1942 (Box 37, Folder 6)
- Manuscript: The 60s, undated (Box 37, Folder 7-9)
- Manuscript: Ada and Jacques, undated (Box 38, Folder 1)
- Manuscript: The Adventures and Misadventures of Oliver, undated (Box 38, Folder 2)
- Manuscript: Autobiography, 2004 (Box 38, Folder 3-5)
- Manuscript: Benedict, 2010 (Box 39, Folder 1-2)
- Manuscript: Burning Valley, circa 1953 (Box 39, Folder 3)
- Manuscript: The Cross on the Hill, undated (Box 39, Folder 4)
- Manuscript: Elaine, 1995 (Box 39, Folder 5)
- Manuscript: The Library, undated (Box 40, Folder 1)
- Manuscript: Once a Red, 1998 (Box 40, Folder 2)
- Manuscript: The Perilous Journey to Meet Joseph P. Weasel, undated (Box 40, Folder 3)
- Manuscript: The Piranha Fish, undated (Box 40, Folder 4)
- Manuscript: Students, 2009 (Box 40, Folder 5-7)
- Manuscript: Writers in Harlem, undated (Box 40, Folder 8)